<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Abouts on codeblue</title>
    <link>/about/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Abouts on codeblue</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/about/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Till D. Best - Bio</title>
      <link>/about/till_best/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/till_best/</guid>
      <description>Till studies medicine at the Charité in Berlin since 2015. For his doctoral thesis, he has joined the Fintelmann lab at Massachusetts General Hospital &amp;amp; Harvard Medical School in 2018. In 2020, he temporarily joined the Institute of Virology at Charité finding yet another team of outstanding scientists that could make use of an amateur coder.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Peter Marquardt - Bio</title>
      <link>/about/peter_marquardt/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/peter_marquardt/</guid>
      <description>Between a father in software and a physician mother, Peter decided to study medicine at RWTH Aachen. Not to make his father feel left out, he started a data science-heavy thesis at the Fintelmann lab at Massachusetts General Hospital &amp;amp; Harvard Medical School in 2019 and is now heading its algorithms &amp;amp; software development team.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About CodeBlue</title>
      <link>/about/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/about/</guid>
      <description>What is &amp;gt;CodeBlue?
In this multimedia blog experiment, we track our journey in the world of medical research, data science and informatics. Rather than discussing specific results, we want to reflect on research practices and career paths informed by our own experiences.
Our goal is to encourage students from all fields of study to consider a career in research by lifting the curtain on our daily life and mindset. Specifically, we hope to demystify the world of science in general and data science in particular.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Codeblue Mission Statement</title>
      <link>/about/mission_statement/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/mission_statement/</guid>
      <description>Welcome to &amp;gt;CodeBlue, a blog experiment centred around medical applications of data science!
Each individual entry is intended to explore an aspect of our work or the environment it takes place in in a self-contained, enjoyable manner. However, across multiple entries we hope to make a contribution towards certain goals close to our hearts:
Most obviously, we want to foster the collaboration between people from medical and data science backgrounds. In the context of this blog, we use the term data science liberally to encompass any computational processing of medical data, ranging from database management to machine learning and app development.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
